foreign
[Music]
as the First new drug approved for
Alzheimer's treatment in nearly 20 years
involves getting IV infusions of an
antibody that targets the amyloid plaque
protein which represents a core brain
pathology of the disease after a phase
one study found no change in the placebo
group but a dramatic reduction in
amyloid plaque burden at different doses
of the drug they jump straight to phase
three two randomized controlled trials
to put it to the test on thousands of
Alzheimer's patients unfortunately both
trials were stopped early after a
futility analysis deemed them failures
as cognition and function continue to
decline in the treatment groups that
shouldn't be surprising since over the
last 20 years there have been more than
20 amyloid targeting therapies that have
universally failed to offer meaningful
cognitive benefit for people with
Alzheimer's disease in fact a 2022
investigation into a seminal paper
implicating amyloid is a causal factor
in Alzheimer's alleged shock kingly
blatant data fraud which has further
tarnished the reputation of the amyloid
Theory so no surprise Ed you Helm
flopped but what happened next was
surprising indeed just when the drugs
prospects seemed dead Biogen the drug
company that developed it launched a
secret campaign codename project Onyx to
use back channels to convince the Food
and Drug Administration to or prove it
anyway they went back to the data and
found a subset of patients in one of the
trials that had a 0.39 increase on an
18-point scale of cognitive function
this was well below the minimal standard
for clinical significance judged to be
at least one or two full points and the
same subset at the same dose in the
other study they funded failed to even
find that effect this kind of post-hoc
after the fact data dredging is like
firing a shotgun in a barn and then
painting a Target around the bullet
holes as one FDA committee statistician
put it FDA viewers thoroughly demolished
biogen's re-analysis concluding there is
no compelling substantial evidence of
treatment effect or disease slowing the
American Academy of Neurology noted that
35 percent of those getting at Academy
suffered swelling or bleeding in the
brain within the first four months of
treatment one in three ten times more
than those in the placebo group so not
surprisingly not a single member of the
FDA expert advisory panel voted in favor
of approval 10 out of 11 voted against
with one quote-unquote uncertain get FDA
ignored its own advisory panel and in
2021 approved the drug anyway
the FDA admitted the submitted data left
residual uncertainties regarding
clinical benefit and so couldn't give it
the standard approval which involves a
designation that the drug is safe and
effective instead they used an
accelerated approval pathway that allows
drugs to be accepted on the basis of
surrogate markers in this case amyloid
clearance
but more than two dozen other amyloid
targeting treatments flopped and despite
convincing plaque reduction there was no
clinical improvements or even worsening
of the disease
the FDA approval of Vatican man proved
to be one of the most controversial and
recent memory the approval despite near
unanimous opposition by its own expert
committee is virtually unprecedented
leaving three of the committee members
to resign and protest one of them called
it probably the worst drug approval
decision in recent U.S history the
response from the scientific community
may best be summed up by a commentary
written by the head of the American
geriatric Society entitled my head just
exploded
the FDA did stipulate that biogem
wouldn't have to run a post-marketing
trial proving that the drug actually has
some benefit but has until 2030 to
report the results meanwhile Biogen is
charging 56 thousand dollars per person
per year for the drug without of pocket
expenses estimated at up to eleven
thousand dollars annually and this
doesn't include the cost of IV
Administration or the sequential four
thousand to seven thousand dollar MRI
scans need to monitor for the brain
bleeds and swelling
yeah the risks far exceed any likely
benefits but shouldn't patients and
their families be able to make up their
own minds the problem is that the FDA
stamp of approval implies at Academy is
safe and effective when at the current
time it appears to be neither
the official position statement of the
American Medical Directors Association
which specializes in long-term care
facilities is that the drug is likely to
have extraordinarily negative
consequences for the millions living
with dementia in this country the
European equivalent of the FDA does not
seem as easily swayed by big Pharma
recommending refusal of the drug I mean
that's the whole point of drug
regulation as one of the former FDA
committee members who resigned put it a
responsibility to help vulnerable
patients and their families not just
from sketchy drugs but also from false
hopes a congressional investigation
concluded FDA approval of that Academy
was Rife with irregularities raising
serious concerns about fda's lapses in
protocol and biogen's disregard of
efficacy of course that didn't stop the
FDA from their 2023 accelerated approval
of a similar antibody akinum absolute
of similar questionable efficacy and
safety
[Music]
foreign